All right, let's get started.
Great.
So for today, we're planning
to finish offline reinforcement
learning.
And along the reward
learning front,
the key goals today
are to figure out
why is task specification hard.
Why do naive methods for
trying to specify rewards fail?
And what are some methods
for learning reward functions
from human supervision?
Cool.
So to start off with finishing
offline reinforcement learning,
we talked about this
problem on Wednesday
where our goal is
to learn a policy
from a batch of existing
data without any online data
collection.
And we assume that the
batch of offline data
is collected by
some unknown policy
that we refer to as the
behavior policy or pi beta.
And our goal is to maximize
rewards under pi theta.
And so we have this challenge
of a distribution shift
between this prior
policy that collected
the data and the policy
that we're optimizing.
One of the challenges
that comes up,
if you try to use traditional
reinforcement learning
algorithms in this setting, is
that-- if, for example, you're
trying to optimize a Q function
to then improve your policy,
then you might query your
Q function on actions
that were sampled from
your learned policy,
and those actions might
not be covered in the data.
And that can cause
overestimation.
And it can cause your Q
function to be inaccurate.
We talked about
this picture where
if we had randomly
initialized some Q function,
and the data only covers actions
along this range for this given
state, then we might--
then when we try
to actually learn
a policy that optimizes
the Q function,
then it will start
to query actions
that are over here because they
randomly have a higher Q value.
And that's one of the key
challenges in offline RL.
Now we talked about
one algorithm that--
I talked about a
couple algorithms.
But the main algorithm that
we talked about last time
was this IQL algorithm.
And IQL addresses the
offline RL problem
by actually avoiding
any sort of queries,
any sort of function queries
beyond the data set actions
altogether.
And it did this by actually
just learning a value function
and a Q function using the
states and actions in the data.
Now if you just do that
with the normal updates,
then you'll learn V pi and Q
pi for the behavior policy.
So you'll learn a value function
for the behavior policy.
And that won't allow
you to improve very much
over the behavior policy.
And so instead, when
learning the value function,
it used this
asymmetric loss to try
to learn a value function
for a policy that's better
than the behavior policy.
And then it learns both the
value function and a Q function.
For the Q function, it
uses a standard L2 loss.
One thing I didn't quite
go over with regard to IQL
is why use an asymmetric
loss for the value function,
but not for the Q function.
And one way to think
about that is you
can think about when
you're taking actions--
when you're rolling
out a policy,
there's two sources
of variability.
One is that the different
actions that you might take.
And one is given an action,
the state that you end up in.
And if you think
about, for example,
the Q function after taking
an action and separately
the value function of the
state that comes after that,
these might be different.
So because you actually--
because there's
randomness in the
environment, the value
function for the next state,
maybe it's something like 8,
because maybe you
got somewhat unlucky
in terms of the next state.
And it might be less
than the Q function
after taking this action.
And likewise for these
other states and actions,
you might have some variability.
So maybe Q of (s, a2).
Maybe that's equal
to 5, because this is
an action that's worse than a1.
Whereas perhaps
when you actually
rolled out a2 in
the environment,
the subsequent state
after taking that action
has a true value of--
maybe a true value of 8.
Maybe you got lucky this time.
Maybe this action is really bad.
In that case, then
Q hat (s, a3).
Maybe it was a
very risky action,
so it has a key
value of negative 5.
And then maybe when you
actually took that risky action
in the environment, maybe
it wasn't quite as bad
as what could have happened.
And so in that case, the
value for that next state
maybe is something
like 0 because it
didn't turn out as bad.
And the reason why I'm writing
out these different numbers
is that we can think about
the asymmetric loss function
when learning the value for IQL.
And the first loss function
when learning the value
is trying to regress to
the different Q values.
And we could either
learn the average Q value
or try to lean towards
the larger Q values.
And if we lean towards
the larger Q values,
that corresponds to
actions that are better.
And so that
corresponds to a policy
that's better than
the behavior policy.
On the contrary, if we instead
use an asymmetric loss function
in the Q function, the
targets for the Q function
correspond to the next value.
And if we instead--
if we use this L2
loss, we'll just
be optimizing for the
average value here.
If we instead use
an asymmetric loss,
then we'd be trying to
regress to the future state
values that are higher,
which would actually
be optimizing for not a better
policy, but a more lucky policy.
And that's something that you
can't control with your actions.
Yeah, so in the IQL
objective, we're
actually training both the
value function and a Q function.
And the reason for that is
because we want to be finding--
the goal is to fit V
hat pi for a pi that
is better than the
behavior policy
or better than the policy
that underlies the data set.
And as we see
here, if we do that
by regressing to these Q
values, then we will pick--
we'll lean towards--
instead of the average,
lean towards the key values that
correspond to better actions.
And so that's learning
a value function
for a policy that's better.
This takes better actions
than the behavior policy.
Now, we can't just use--
it's useful to have a Q function
and not just a value function,
because the Q function is
what helps us figure out
which actions are
better when we use
advantage-weighted
regression and so forth.
And so we also learn
a Q function as well.
But for that, we
use asymmetric loss
so that we're not
optimizing for being lucky.
OK.
So IQL was one way to learn a
policy from an offline data set.
There's also some
other ways to do it.
And in particular, we'll talk
about one more way, one more
algorithm.
And in this case,
we're still going
to try to estimate the value.
We're still going to actually
query actions from our policy.
And we want to think about how
to discourage overestimation
and discourage the RL
algorithm from taking actions
that you think might have high
Q value because they're out
of distribution.
And so one idea is, what if we
just outside of the data support
try to minimize the Q values?
Can we just basically
take this part
and try to push down
on the Q values that
are out of distribution?
And if we did
that, then we would
be pessimistic or
conservative with regard
to everything that's out
of distribution and not
as conservative
when we're actually
in the support of the data.
And so we could formulate some
loss function that does this.
And what this would
look like is you're
trying to fit a Q function.
And you will have your
standard loss for your critic,
for your value function.
I'll call this L critic.
Then we could also
add a loss function.
This is for-- we're trying
to fit the Q function.
So maybe that Q function
has parameters phi.
And then we could add
an additional term
that is trying to
additionally minimize
the key values on actions
that are out of distribution.
So we would try to be
minimizing our Q values.
And in particular, we want
to minimize key values
for our distribution actions.
And so this would
be an expectation
over states sampled from
your data set and actions
sampled from some other
distribution that's
not the data set.
And ideally, this
distribution would
cover the
out-of-distribution actions
that your policy
might be considering.
So this is some
other distribution.
That distribution would probably
be a function of [? f. ?]
Now if you want to
think about which
out-of-distribution actions your
policy might be considering,
your policy is going
to be considering
the out-of-distribution
actions that have high Q value.
And so one initial version
that we could do here
is we could pick a mu,
pick this distribution,
such that it has high Q
values, because our policy will
be trying to take actions
that have high Q values.
And so what this would look
like is minimizing our critic
parameters and
choosing a mu such
that it's maximizing
the Q values.
So what this will
do is it will have--
it will try to optimize
a critic and then
minimize the Q
values for actions
that have a high Q value.
Now this is version 1.
We're going to be pushing
down on large Q values.
You can show with this
version that if you have
a large enough alpha, if you--
you don't necessarily-- you
want to have some sort of weight
on this objective.
This is going to be
a hyperparameter.
If you have a
large enough alpha,
you can show that the critic
that you learned from this
is going to be a lower bound
on the true Q function.
And so then what this
would look like is
if you have some plot
of your Q functions
for a different action, and
if your data support is maybe
something like this,
something that you might learn
is a lower bound on
the true Q function,
where this latter one
is going to be Q hat.
Now, one downside
with this is that you
might be a little
bit too pessimistic,
because this is actually
going to be pushing down
on all Q values.
But we know that
for the Q values,
for the actions in the data
set, for the part that's
in the support of our
data set, these actions
we have more data for.
And so we don't necessarily
want to be pushing down
on the key values
for those actions.
And so we could
do is we could add
a term that basically cancels
out this term for the data
sets in the actions.
And so what that
would do is just--
what that would
look like is simply
taking this same exact
term and subtracting it
for states in the data set, but
also actions in the data set.
So we're going to be minimizing
the Q values for actions
from this distribution
and maximizing
for actions in the data set.
And this will hopefully-- the
goal of this would be to get a Q
function that inside the
support of the data--
it's not a very good marker.
That's inside the support of
the data is maybe very accurate.
And then for the things
outside the support of the data
has a low Q values,
because we know
that outside the
support of the data,
we aren't going to be able to
learn an accurate Q function.
Yeah, so the question
is, does this
affect your ability to
generalize outside the support
of the data?
So certainly, it does.
It's going to cause you
to be basically more
pessimistic outside of
the support of the data.
This hyperparameter
alpha is going
to control how
pessimistic you are.
And if you think that you're
in a regime where you might
be able to generalize
better, then you
could choose an
alpha that is smaller
so that you're using more of
the original critic objective
and less of this
regularization term.
Yeah.
The question is, should
it be Q or Q hat?
Right.
So it should be Q hat phi.
So this is our--
this is the Q function that
we're learning right here.
The notation on the slide
is slightly different.
Sorry for the difference there.
So on the slides, we're
treating Q as the thing
that we're minimizing.
And if we view it instead of
minimizing these parameters,
then this is how
we would write it.
Yeah, so the question
is, what is mu?
Is it this fake policy
that's outside the support?
You can think of mu as
sort of as a policy.
It's not actually the policy
that we're going to be running,
but it's essentially going to be
something that is trying to seek
out the Q values that have--
the Q values that--
or the actions
that have high Q value so
that if, for example, you're
over here, you would minimize
the key values there.
And yeah, it's
basically something
that's trying to seek
out large key values,
either in or outside
the distribution.
Once it gets inside
the distribution,
you're then going to be
canceling out with this term.
And so then you'll have
a more accurate estimate
inside the support of the data.
The question is, does it mop
out the Q for the actions
outside the support.
And yeah, that's
basically what it's doing.
Oh, in terms of--
the question is,
what does it mean to maximize
mu in terms of the distribution?
It basically means that we're
going to be picking a mu such
that it has high Q values.
In practice, we'll
actually see in a minute.
We can actually not have
to explicitly represent
mu for some choices, but we'll
talk about that in a second.
The question is, if
our goal is to minimize
Q for things outside the
training distribution,
why not just do normal
behavior cloning?
So one of the things that's
nice about this algorithm
is it has the potential to do
better than behavior cloning.
So any sort of RL method
will be leveraging the reward
information to learn a policy
that has high Q values.
And so you can actually
use this method
to do considerably better
than behavior cloning.
And then we also
talked on Wednesday
about a method that can also do
better by behavior cloning just
by ranking things.
Generally, methods that try
to train the policy on only
the actions in the
distribution are generally
a valid way to do offline RL.
This is thinking about an
alternative way to do it.
OK.
So in terms of--
when we introduced
this last term,
we're actually no
longer guaranteed
to have a lower bound on the
Q function for all states
and actions.
But we're actually
guaranteed an expectation
to have a lower bound for all
the states in our data set.
I'm not going to go through
the derivation for this,
but it's a nice property
to have that you
will get some sort of lower
bound on the true Q function.
And it suggests that it's a
reasonable objective to use.
[? If ?] alpha is 0,
it does not hold--
alpha does need to
be large enough.
I can't remember the
exact conditions on alpha.
But you could take a look at
the CQL paper for the proof.
Cool.
So this is an algorithm called
conservative Q-learning.
In terms of the
full algorithm, we
will optimize this objective
using our data set.
And then we'll get a Q
function as a result of this.
And then after we
optimize our Q function,
we can then update
our policy and then
repeat that process to--
and yeah.
If the actions are discrete,
then you can just in some ways
read out the actions by
picking the actions that
have maximum probability.
If they're continuous,
then you'll
need to use some sort of
update to optimize your policy.
And you'll be wanting to
optimize your policy such
that you are picking actions
that have high Q value.
Cool.
So we talked about this mu term.
And in practice, if we had
to construct this mu term,
that would be annoying, and
it would add a moving part
to the algorithm.
And so in terms of thinking
what this mu should be,
you want to pick a mu that is
going to actually have high Q
values, because that would
allow it to push down
erroneously large Q values.
And when you apply it on
things with small Q values,
it's not really going to
have a meaningful effect.
But you also don't want to--
you want it to--
you want it to be considering
actions that are not just
like exactly the
one largest Q value.
And as written, this
mu term might actually
collapse to be
very deterministic
and just pick the one action
that has the largest Q value.
And so you can think of--
in this case, you can think of
instead of just maximizing mu,
you could think of
adding a regularizer
to mu that encourages
it to consider
a broader set of actions.
And specifically,
you can think of that
as choosing a mu
that's maximizing Q
but also has some entropy to it.
And so if you view this
as adding a regularizer,
then you could choose a
mu that has high entropy,
meaning that it is a
broader distribution.
And it turns out that if you--
for this equation, if you're
trying to choose large Qs
and choose a distribution that
has wider, larger entropy,
then you can
actually write down--
you can write down what this
looks like in closed form.
And in particular, for
maximizing Q and maximizing
entropy, you can show
that the optimal mu
is proportional to the
exponentiated Q values.
Won't go into the
derivation for this.
We possibly will
post something on Ed
after lecture if
you're interested.
And then this term turns
out to simply come out
to a log [? sum ?] x over
your Q values without having
to construct an explicit mu.
And so then the
final objective is
going to look something like--
will look something like the
loss function for the critic
plus the log [? sum ?] x of Q of
(s, a) with an alpha term here
minus alpha times the expected
Q values for states and actions
in your data set.
And you will-- this means
that you don't actually
need to construct mu directly.
This was the only term
that depended on mu.
And we just replaced this
with this term right here.
Yeah, so if there's a
continuous action space,
then you'll want to
sample to estimate this.
OK.
Cool.
So for this algorithm called
CQL or conservative Q-learning,
I figured [INAUDIBLE]
application
of this just as an example.
We've seen a lot of
applications in robotics
and talked about
driving and so forth.
It turns out that
some folks at LinkedIn
use this algorithm
to optimize a policy
for sending notifications,
like email notifications,
for example.
And usually, when you
send notifications,
you want to optimize for
things like how much people
are clicking on it, because
that means that it is something
that they're potentially
interested in,
but also want to minimize
the total number of times
that you're sending
them a notification
so that you're not
spamming the user.
You might also care about
weekly active users.
And they took the
double DQN algorithm.
They also had their
existing system,
which is the baseline here.
And they also tried applying the
CQL terms to a DQN objective.
And they found that when you
added CQL using an offline data
set and then ran that policy
in an online A/B test,
they were able to get a higher
click-through rate, a lower
number of total notifications,
and also a slight increase
in user usage.
So yeah.
This is one example
of a scenario where
offline RL and
specifically this algorithm
was used in a fairly
real-world scenario.
Yeah, so the question
is, why do we
want to be conservative
in the first place?
So this really comes down to
the very initial motivation
for offline RL, which is
that outside of the support
of the data, when you
cannot collect online data,
you can't really learn a policy
that's far beyond the data.
And one reason to
be conservative
is specifically trying
to be conservative
outside the support of
the data, because those
are the regimes where you
don't have the ability
to collect more data.
And if you try to learn--
if you assume that you can
go far beyond the data,
then you might learn an
inaccurate Q function
and, as a result, might
learn a poor policy.
OK.
So to summarize, online
data is expensive.
Using offline data is useful.
A key challenge that
comes up in offline RL
is overestimation because of
the shift between the policy
and the data and the policy
that you're learning.
And we talked about a
few different approaches
for doing this.
And the one we
talked about today
was to try to explicitly
penalize Q values.
And offline RL
methods are allowed--
are able to improve over
imitation learning, including
filtered imitation learning,
by stitching together
good behaviors and leveraging
reward information.
Cool.
So let's shift gears and
talk about reward learning.
So in everything that
we've talked about so far--
well, except for
imitation learning--
we've been trying to
maximize the sum of rewards.
And there's this
question of, where
do the rewards come
from in the first place,
and where do we get them?
And some of the very initial use
cases of reinforcement learning
were with computer
games, where you can just
use the score of the game
as your reward function,
and then get a player that
plays the game very well.
But in real-world
scenarios, you often
don't get rewards as directly,
especially when we're developing
computers to do things.
So if you wanted to develop
a robot that could pour water
from a pitcher into a cup is
fairly complex for a robot
to do, although young children
are able to do it fairly well.
Humans maybe get
some kind of reward
when they drink the water
and some sort of satisfaction
from that.
But robots do not get
that kind of satisfaction.
And so if you were to
try to get a reward
function for this
kind of pouring task,
then you would need to
think about how to represent
where the water is.
Did you spill any water?
Did the water get into
the cup and so forth?
So it's pretty challenging to
get a reward function for that.
If you have some kind
of dialogue situation,
you're trying to
develop a chatbot,
people don't directly tell
you that was a reward of 1.
That was a reward of 10.
And so you need
to think about how
to get a reward function that's
informative for reinforcement
learning.
Likewise, in autonomous driving,
the real world doesn't just
give you reward functions, and
you need to think about how--
a number of different
factors, like the rules
of the road, how comfortable is
it for the user, and so forth.
So in some cases, we can use
a proxy for the true reward.
And you could have a
human giving the rewards
like maybe giving like 1 if that
was successful, 0 otherwise.
You might have some
proxy in terms of things
like click-through rate.
That's a proxy.
We don't necessarily care
about humans clicking on things
inherently, but it's a proxy
for what we might care about.
But even with proxies,
there's a lot of downsides.
And it's worth thinking
about if there's other ways
to provide supervision
to reinforcement learning
algorithms.
We've seen one alternative
approach so far,
which is just to use
imitation learning.
And you don't need
any reward function
if you use imitation learning.
But when you use
imitation learning,
you're not really thinking
about outcomes and optimizing
for a particular outcome.
You're just optimizing
for mimicking the actions.
You might also have
scenarios where
it's hard to provide
demonstrations,
or where the expert has
different degrees of freedom.
That might make it hard
to get good demonstration
data for imitation.
And so a lot of
reward learning is
to think about what is the
underlying outcome that we
want to see.
What is the expert
trying to achieve?
What do humans want?
So people are able
to infer rewards.
There's a few other examples.
Lots of fun videos, where
even very small kids are
able to figure out what is
the reward function, what
is the objective, and
be able to even optimize
that to help the person.
OK.
So how do we learn rewards?
We'll talk about two
approaches for doing this.
One is from examples of
goals, and another one
is from human preferences.
So one of the simplest things
we could consider doing
is try to give examples of
what success looks like,
and then train a classifier to
predict success versus failure.
So, for example, if
we wanted a robot
to put a pencil case
behind a notebook,
we give it a few
examples of what
that looks like, give it a few
negative examples of scenarios
where it's not
behind the notebook,
and then train a
binary classifier
to be able to predict that
the positive examples should
be labeled with 1,
the negative examples
should be labeled with 0.
And then you could use the
output of this binary classifier
as your reward signal.
So specifically, what
this would look like is
you first collect examples
of successful states,
unsuccessful states.
You can think of this as states
within some sort of goal set
and states outside
of that goal set,
and then train a
binary classifier,
and then run reinforcement
learning with this classifier.
Does anyone have thoughts
on what could go wrong
if you took this approach?
Yeah, so one downside
with this approach
is that it's going to give
you a very sparse reward.
It's just going to
tell you, are you
within this set of goal states,
or are you outside of it?
And you would need
to figure out how
to make progress towards that.
Is there any other challenges
or any other things
that might go wrong?
Yeah, so a second
thing that might happen
is it might learn to
fool the classifier,
but not actually do the task
that you're interested in.
And in particular, when
you train a classifier,
it's trained on some
distribution of examples
that you provided.
But the policy that
you're learning
has the ability to visit
lots of different states,
including states that are
different from the initial data
set.
And in some ways, analogous
to some of the challenges
we saw in offline RL.
When you're optimizing
against this classifier,
you can hack it or fool
it and find states where
that classifier is inaccurate.
And when it's inaccurate,
some of the times
it might be optimistic
about how to do the task.
So the first answer
was absolutely correct.
It does provide a sparse signal.
But one especially thing
that can go extra wrong here
is that the RL algorithm
will seek out states
that the classifier
thinks are good.
And it might simply find states
that the classifier wasn't
trained on, and
essentially exploiting
the classifier's weaknesses.
So can we prevent the algorithm
from exploiting the weaknesses?
In some ways, it's
actually nice that we had--
we're talking about this at the
same time in which we talked
about CQL, because we can
actually use an approach that's
very similar to CQL for
preventing the RL algorithm
from exploiting the weaknesses.
And in particular, say that you
have some kind of positive goal
states over here where--
I don't know.
In the pencil case
example, maybe this
is where the pencil
case should be.
You could also just
generally think of it
as some abstract space.
And then you also have
negative examples over here.
Maybe this is a
bad place to go to.
And then your classifier, when
you train a binary classifier,
it will learn some sort of
decision boundary like this.
And then when you
train a policy, when
it sees that the stuff
over here is positive
and the stuff over
here is negative,
maybe we can also
specify the direction
of our binary classifier.
Then your RL algorithm, it might
learn to go somewhere over here.
And maybe some of these
states are good, but maybe
also some of these
states are not so good.
And if we want to avoid
exploiting the classifier,
one simple thing
that we could do
is we could take these states
that we visited with our policy,
and we could then label them
as additional data points
for training our classifier.
Now we don't necessarily-- if
we don't have a good reward
function and we don't
want supervision online,
then we don't know exactly
what the labels should be.
And one thing that we could do
is simply to be conservative.
We could label
these as negatives
and say that all of
these were states
that were failures, essentially,
and then retrain our classifier.
And if we retrain
our classifier,
we would then get a classifier
that maybe looks like this.
And then maybe our
policy visits over here.
And then you eventually
learn a classifier
that is more accurate
around these states.
Is there any--
well, OK.
So let's walk through what
this would look explicitly.
So we could add
states that the RL
algorithm visits as negative
examples for the classifier.
So specifically,
we would collect
some initial set of success
states and unsuccessful states.
And then we would
update our classifier
and train it to classify
the success states
and the unsuccessful states.
Then we would collect some
experience using our policy
and update our policy using
the classifier-based reward.
And then we'd add the visited
states to our negative examples,
and then reupdate our classifier
using those negative states.
Does anyone have concerns
about this algorithm?
The concern there is
that you might not
learn a very robust
classifier, and you
might overfit to the
positives in your data set.
And in particular, if you have
a small number of positives,
then you might learn a decision
boundary that is very--
only contains each
of these positives
and doesn't contain the
things right around them.
And so one thing that
you can do for that
is to try to regularize
your classifier
to try to prevent
that overfitting.
And even standard regularizers
can be helpful for that.
You can encourage it
to be more smooth.
Any other concerns
about this algorithm?
Yeah, so one of
the challenges that
can come up with
this algorithm is
that you're going to be
adding more and more negatives
to your data set.
And one really
critical thing here
is that if you keep on
adding negatives to your data
set and don't rebalance
your data set,
then it might just predict
negative everywhere.
And so one critical thing here
is to balance the data set 50/50
so that the negatives account
for half of the data that
you're sampling, and the
positives account for the other
half of the data
that you're sampling.
Yeah, so the question
was that at some point
your original negatives will
be overwhelmed by the sample
negatives.
And does it make
sense to balance them?
Certainly, you could do that.
It depends on how large
your initial negatives are.
And so that's
something to consider.
One of the things
that will happen
is that your policy
will actually
start visiting the states here.
And it might visit
like even exactly
the same states
as the positives.
And you're then going to be
labeling these as negatives.
Now those labels are incorrect.
Those states are
actually true positives.
And this also alludes to
the overfitting comment
at the beginning.
But it actually turns out that
if you balance your data set,
this might actually be OK and
if you use enough regularization
or have a large enough
positive and negative data set.
And the reason why
this might be OK
is that when you
use balancing, it
will ensure that the half of
the data set will be positives.
And even if-- let's say that--
OK, so we know that
50% of the data set
is going to be like
true positives.
And then for the other
part of the data set,
some proportion of it
will be false negatives
and some proportion of it
will be true negatives.
Let's say that we've
gotten to the point where
for the other 50%, 40% is
a false negative, meaning
that it's labeled as a negative,
but it's actually a positive.
And 10%, including our
original negatives,
corresponds to true negatives.
Then in this case,
as long as we're
balancing our data set, for a
positive, it will still output--
it won't output
like probability 1
that something is a positive
because of all these here.
But it's still going to output
a probability that something
is positive that's higher
than 50% and probability
that's higher than the
probability that it is negative.
And so, yeah, specifically,
with balancing,
you can always expect
that the probability
of a true positive under
our classifier, this
will always be--
if the classifier is
training properly,
this will always be
greater than 50%,
because as long as this
data set is not like--
if it's all the way like 50--
like entirely false negatives,
then it will be exactly 50%.
But as long as you have
some true negatives around,
including your original
set of negatives,
then it'll be
strictly above 0.5.
And the probability of a true
negative will be less than 0.5.
The question is,
would this be resolved
if we use confidence
intervals instead of 0 or 1?
So you can also use this
probability as the reward
and not threshold it.
And that is also fine.
In terms of
confidence intervals,
that could also
potentially be helpful,
although I haven't
thought too much about it.
And you would need probably a
slightly more sophisticated RL
method.
Yeah, so if you're in a scenario
where you visit a state that's
very hard to distinguish
between them,
then if you have
regularization, it's
likely to label
it as a positive,
because the regularization
will encourage the function
to be smooth.
But it comes down a lot
to how different it is.
Yeah.
So the question
is, would this be
solved if we use a generative
adversarial network where
the classifier is--
the reward is the discriminator
and the generator is the agent?
It turns out that
this actually--
OK, I don't have-- this is
like two slides from now.
But it turns out
that this actually
is exactly a generative
adversarial network.
So you can think
of this classifier
as a discriminator that's
trying to discriminate
between the positive
examples that we gave
and everything that
the policy is visiting.
And the generator in a
generative adversarial network
is the policy.
You don't necessarily
need to know
about exactly what generative
adversarial networks or GANs
are.
But if you do know
what they are,
this is basically
exactly a form of a GAN.
Yeah, so the question is,
after we run a trajectory,
are we seeing what
the true label is?
And the answer to that is no.
So we're assuming that we don't
get any more human supervision
other than the initial
training data set.
Now one other thing
that you can do here
that makes this a little bit
potentially easier is you
could also label some of the
data as positives or negatives
as well, and use
that to continue
to update your classifier.
And so that's also a
very valid approach.
And there's ways to label
only some of the data
so that you don't have to
label every single trajectory
that the policy is doing.
And that could also help
stabilize the training.
One example of using this
kind of approach in robotics
is a paper that took
50 demonstrations.
It used the final
states as successes
for training the classifier.
It initializes a replay buffer
with the demonstrations.
And if you directly
imitate the demonstrations,
the success rate is around 26%,
because 50 demonstrations is not
that much.
And even if you
collect more, it would
be hard to get to 100% success.
And then if instead you use
this initialization and run
RL with a classifier
learned in this way,
then you get a policy that has,
in this case, a 62% success
rate.
Not awesome yet,
but something that's
substantially higher
than the success
rate of imitation learning.
And one thing that we found that
we talked about that was also
we found in this research
is that it's actually
very important to
regularize the classifier
to help it not overfit to
just the positive, the 50
positive examples that were
provided at the beginning.
OK.
And as aside, this
is how GANs work.
The generative
adversarial networks
are a form of generative model.
They've often been used
for image generation.
And the key idea is
to train a classifier
between the real examples,
like the real positives,
and the generated data, like the
states that the policy visits.
And you try to train a
generator that this classifier--
tried to generate such
that it generates things
that the classifier
thinks is real.
GANs have been used in
a variety of places.
Here are some examples of
images generated by a GAN.
Here's a cool video of an
astronaut dancing on Mars,
and later walking his dog
on Mars that also uses
generative adversarial network.
Cool.
Now as a recap, we talked
about training classifiers.
These classifiers
can be exploited
when you optimize against them.
And the solution is that during
the RL process, if we update
the classifier using negatives
visited by the policy, then
you can avoid it
being exploited.
One of the things
that didn't quite
have-- that I wanted to skip
today, because we don't have
too much time and need to
talk about preferences--
but you can also actually learn
not just goal classifiers.
But you can actually learn
full reward functions.
If you use all of the states in
the demo as positive examples
and all of the states in your
policy rollouts as negatives,
then you can show
that that's actually--
we'll be trying
to learn a reward
function over
state distributions
rather than just goal states.
Cool.
On the upside, this is a
very practical framework.
Adversarial training, this
adding these as negatives.
It can be unstable.
There are a variety of
regularization tricks.
You can actually take them just
directly from the GAN literature
and apply them.
And that is quite helpful.
And then one other
big downside here
is that this requires
examples of what the goal is,
like what the
desired behavior is.
And sometimes generating
those examples
can be challenging
or time-consuming.
OK.
So that's learning
from example goals.
Now let's talk about
learning from preferences.
And this is
specifically-- we're going
to talk less about
goal classifiers
and talk more about
scenarios where we don't just
want to reach states
within some goal set,
but we actually want
to potentially learn
like good behavior
versus bad behavior.
And that might
encapsulate something
beyond just reaching
a good state.
And instead of requiring example
demonstrations or example goals
or in addition to that, we
might want to provide feedback
on the full rollout.
Now one option
that we could do is
we could just ask how
good is this trajectory.
So say that you wanted to
start at this blue dot,
and you want to reach the star
as efficiently as possible.
So it's actually hard.
Now another way to
frame this question
is, which trajectory is better?
So who thinks the blue
trajectory is better
than the pink trajectory?
OK, everyone thinks the blue.
So that's a much easier
question to answer, right?
So these kind of
relative preferences
are often easier to provide than
evaluating absolute performance
of a trajectory.
And this is true
for lines in 2D,
but it's also true
in other use cases,
many real-world
use cases as well.
So maybe we can use
these kind of preferences
to get a reward function.
So say that we--
human told us that one
trajectory was better
than another trajectory.
Then probably one way to think
about what they're saying
is that the sum of rewards
for the states in that
trajectory-- so for the states
and actions in the better
trajectory.
This should probably be
larger than the sum of rewards
for the states and actions
in the trajectory that
was said to be worse.
And I'm using W and L to refer
to the winning trajectory
and the losing trajectory.
And maybe we'll
write this as the--
when we say that the
winning trajectory is better
than the losing
trajectory, we'll
write this with this notation.
So any individual preference
label that's binary saying A
is better than B tells us
a little bit of information
about the reward.
And from there, we
want to figure out
how to aggregate a number
of these preference labels
to learn a reward function.
And so we'll assume
that we have some data
set of these pairs where we
have a pair of trajectories.
We are told which one is the
good one and which one is--
or which one is better
than the other one.
And we want to be able
to use this data set
to learn a reward function.
And one perhaps simple way to
do this is we want to model--
we need some way to write
down an objective for a reward
function.
Let's also say that
our reward function--
let's model it as
a neural network.
So our reward function
will have some parameters.
And then you can
think of it as taking
as input a state and action
and outputting a scalar reward
value.
So if you want to write down an
objective for this, one thing
we could do--
let's say that this is
used similar shorthand
to what we've used before.
This is the reward
of the trajectory.
This expression right here.
Then maybe we could say that if
we took the reward of the better
trajectory and subtracted the
reward of the trajectory that's
worse, then we want this
quantity to be positive.
So that's one starting point.
And from there, we could--
we like to do
maximum likelihood.
We like to think
about probabilities
and do maximum likelihood
training in machine learning,
in general.
So we could try to represent the
probability that a trajectory is
better than--
one trajectory is better
than another trajectory.
And so we could do is
we could take this.
We could pass this into
a sigmoid function, which
will squash it between 0 and
1, and then represent that
as the probability that
the winning trajectory is
better than the trajectory
that was marked as inferior.
And then if we did
this, then we could
try to maximize the probability
under our reward function.
So we could try to
then optimize a reward
function such that the prob--
such that you're maximizing
this probability.
So this would be then summed
over the trajectory pairs
in our data set.
And so specifically, we
would take each of the pairs,
take the sum of rewards.
For each of these, subtract
them, take a sigmoid,
and then try to maximize that
by running gradient descent.
It's also worth
mentioning these taus.
You could do it on
a full trajectory,
but in some scenarios,
if a full trajectory
is driving from Palo Alto to San
Francisco or cleaning a kitchen,
then there's many different
subcomponents of that.
And it might be hard.
There might be some parts of
that trajectory that are better
and some parts that are worse.
And so you could also do
this on partial trajectories
and say like this part
of this trajectory
is better than this part.
So you don't have to do
it on full trajectories.
We want to reward such that the
sum of rewards for the better
trajectory is higher than the
sum of the rewards for the worst
trajectory.
Humans are classifying
which trajectory's better.
We want the reward to be
discriminative of which
trajectory is better.
And so we define
this probability
that one trajectory is better
than another trajectory.
And then with this
probability, we
can try to maximize the
reward parameters such
that this is true.
Yeah, so the question
was the human
isn't telling us how much
better a trajectory is.
And you could have a scenario
where maybe one trajectory is
like this, one
trajectory is like this,
and then a third
trajectory is like--
I don't know-- going all the
way over here or something.
And this objective isn't
taking into account
the fact that the
preference of this over this
is a smaller preference than the
preference of this over this.
When you end up
optimizing this objective,
oftentimes, it will
actually turn out
that it will assign something.
Well, so I guess a
couple of things here.
So if you have a
lot of data, then it
will also tell you that
this, the solid green one,
is better than this one.
And so you could actually get
lots of pairwise preferences
on them.
And so because of those
pairwise preferences,
you'll see a ranking, like
this is better than this.
This is better than this.
And when you do that, that'll
force the reward function
to assign a much higher
reward value to this one
compared to this one.
So it will already
do what you want.
You could also-- there's
a couple other ways
to get this information.
Sometimes when you actually
ask humans for preferences,
sometimes you also
just give them a batch
and tell them to rank as well.
And that would make
this even more explicit.
So the complete algorithm for
what this looks like is you
have some data set
of trajectories.
You're going to sample
batches of k trajectories.
And then ask a human to
rank those k trajectories.
For language models
when you do this-- so
this is actually a common
way to learn reward functions
for language models.
And you'll often actually use
the same prompt and sample k
responses and then ask them
to rank those k responses.
And this is useful because
these trajectories all
start from some initial point.
You can think of this as
starting from the same prompt.
But you might have
other responses
that are like starting from
a different prompt over here.
And for a different prompt or
from a different starting place,
it's a lot harder to talk
about like, is this better--
like, is this black one
better than this green one?
It got there-- maybe
got here faster,
but it also had-- it was
an easier starting point.
And so oftentimes,
we'll try to sample
a batch of
trajectories that have
a similar starting position.
Then we will compute the rewards
under our current reward model,
essentially do a
forward pass, and sum
over the states and actions.
And then we can
compute the gradient,
do a backward pass
using our objective,
where this is for
every pair of--
for each pair
within the ranking.
So there's k choose 2 different
combinations of pairs.
And if you have a ranking, then
you'll have a full set of k
choose 2 labels.
Then you can update theta
using the computed gradient.
And then you can also
repeat this process.
And repeating this just
corresponds to doing
gradient descent on your
objective on a single data set.
Now one thing that
you can also do
is you can also do this in the
loop of reinforcement learning.
So you have your samples
from your policy.
And then you can ask for humans
to rank them and then update
your rewards.
And then after you have
your updated reward model,
then maybe your reward
model is more accurate.
And maybe you want to be going
like here, for example, instead
of going here.
Then you could then reupdate
your reward function
and then update your policy
again, and then get new rollouts
for your policy.
Ask a human to label
those rollouts,
reupdate your reward
function, and repeat.
OK.
So that's how we can
learn from preferences.
There's a few examples of this.
So the first time--
or some of the
first times people
have learned from preferences
were in some simulated settings.
So in this case, if you want
to get this simulated thing
to do a backflip.
It's very hard to write a reward
function for doing a backflip.
And so they used 900 queries.
They asked humans 900 times
like, is this better than this?
They actually did it in the
loop of reinforcement learning.
And they got a policy
that is able to learn
how to do a backflip,
and in the process also
learn a reward function for
a human-preferred backflip.
Also, in driving, it's very
hard to get reward functions.
And so there was work that
used this kind of approach
to learn things
like how much does
it matter to stay
within your lane,
keep a certain speed,
collision avoidance,
those sorts of things.
And you would imagine
that collision avoidance
is much, much more important
than keeping a certain speed,
for example.
And you can learn a
reward function that way.
Cool.
And then there's
also language models.
So this has been
a very popular way
to learn rewards
for language models.
And you can have some prompt
like, how do I cook an omelet?
Then you can sample
from your language model
two different responses
for that prompt.
Then we ask a person
which response is better.
When we're doing training,
we might actually
pay people to label our data.
You might have also--
if you've interacted
with ChatGPT,
sometimes it might have asked
you these sorts of things.
You're providing labels
to give OpenAI the ability
to learn a reward function that
is better for your preferences.
And then once you have the
things that are better,
then you can train
a reward model
that judges how good a response
y is for a given prompt.
And so then in terms of what
the kind of full language model
pipeline is, if you wanted to
train something like ChatGPT,
first, you'll do some
large-scale pre-training
on very, very large
mixed quality data.
With just predicting
the next token,
then you typically
have a second stage,
which is to fine-tune
on higher quality data.
And in particular,
after step one,
before you do any kind
of supervised fine-tuning
or reinforcement
learning, you'll
get a reward, a language model
that knows a lot of things,
but is not easy to
control or to get it
to do what you want it to do.
And it might not
answer questions.
It might not do
what you requested.
It might just predict
reasonable next tokens
that come after that.
Whereas in supervised
fine-tuning,
we can generate a
higher quality data
set that has for a given prompt,
this is how you should reply.
And so we do some
kind of imitation
learning on that data set.
And then there's a
third step, which
is to use the human
feedback and then fine-tune
the model that you got
from supervised fine-tuning
on higher quality
preference data.
And what this third
step looks like is first
you gather the preference data.
There are also actually
existing preference data
sets that you can use as well.
You don't have to necessarily--
you don't necessarily
have to collect it
on using your model.
Second, you'll
train a reward model
that is judging how
good a response is.
And then lastly,
you'll do reinforcement
learning to maximize
that reward function.
We will talk more about
preference learning on Wednesday
next week.
But one somewhat
common approach is
to use PPO to
maximize the reward.
The question is, is
x just the prompt,
or is it the whole history?
Oftentimes, it's
the whole history.
And you can sort of--
yeah, oftentimes,
when you-- generally,
also when you formulate RL
problems for language models,
you will have--
you can model it as
a sequential problem.
But you can also--
there's a way to--
a simpler but more
crude way to model
it, which is to use all
the history and just
treat the next
response as the thing
that you're optimizing over.
So the question is, how do we
go from preference rankings
to this probability right here?
So in our preferences,
we're saying
that we might have
a ranking saying
like A is better than B
which is better than C.
If we have a ranking
of k trajectories,
then we can formulate k
choose 2 pairs where--
and within each pair we'll
have an A is better than B,
or B is better than A.
We're using tau w to represent
the response or the trajectory
that was preferred,
and tau l to represent
the one that was dispreferred.
And then we sample one of
those pairs, one of those k
choose pairs.
And then we plug it into
this equation right here.
So you're asking, what is
the sigma function or--?
yeah, so the sigma
function here--
this is a sigmoid.
So it is basically a
function that squashes
the values between 0 and 1.
And so it's just a very
simple function that--
I can't remember.
I think it looks something
like this, where this is 1.
So yeah, I'm just using sigma.
This is sigma right here.
So it's just this
function right here.
OK.
One other thing you can do is
instead of using human feedback,
you could also have an AI model.
You could ask a strong model
like, is this better than this?
One thing that I'll
note is when you
are thinking about what is
preferred and dispreferred,
there are a variety
of different axes
in which something might be
preferred or dispreferred.
And so you could--
in some cases, you might be
able to ask for certain things
that you care about
from the model.
This is often referred to
as reinforcement learning
with AI feedback.
As one example of a
use case, the people
have used this to
try to prevent models
from producing harmful content.
And so they will feed two
responses into the model
and ask the model which
response is less harmful.
One insight here
is that critique is
often easier than generation.
And so this is
one of the reasons
why you might be able to get a
stronger model with AI feedback
than otherwise.
And there have been
some works that
show that if you use this kind
of feedback, this AI feedback,
you can get an improvement
in model performance
on different axes.
OK.
So a summary of
reward learning--
rewards cannot be
taken for granted.
We've talked about
learning from goals.
We talked about learning
from human preferences.
For goals, it's quite practical.
Adversarial training can be a
little bit tricky to optimize,
and it requires examples
of desired behavior.
With preferences,
pairwise preferences
are really easy to provide.
It doesn't require example
goals or example demonstrations.
It has been deployed at
really, really large scales
with language models.
It may require some
supervision in the loop
of reinforcement learning.
One other thing that I encourage
everyone to think about
is goals and human preferences,
those are some form of feedback,
but there's a lot of
other ways that we
might be able to provide
supervision to agents
that are trying to learn.
You could even verbally
tell it some information
like, that was good,
or that was helpful,
or that was helpful but
mean, or something like that.
And you could think of other
ways of providing supervision.
And I think that this is
an area of research that--
yeah-- where I
think that there's
more things that could be done.
One other thing
that I'll mention
is there's also some cool work
in the reinforcement learning
research landscape,
where you can potentially
have reinforcement
learning agents propose
their own goals rather than
having a human provide a goal.
This is often referred
to as this area
of unsupervised reinforcement
learning, where human is not
telling the agent
what it should do.
Instead, the agent should have
its own sort of curiosity.
One example of this
is you can have
one agent setting a goal,
another agent trying
to reach the goal.
And you can formulate this
as a game between these two
different agents.
And there's, yeah,
some cool work that
shows that you can have that--
if you have these two
different agents that
are trying to play against each
other, where one is the goal
setter, one is trying
to reach the goals,
you can get some kind of
cool behavior as a result.